<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SCIL | The Code Dump]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.codelord.net/category/scil/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.codelord.net/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-25T22:57:11+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.codelord.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aviv Ben-Yosef]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[aviv.by+blog@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crafting Up - Community is Key]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.codelord.net/2011/03/27/crafting-up-community-is-key/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-27T22:12:30+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.codelord.net/2011/03/27/crafting-up-community-is-key</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been almost a year now since the founding of our local <a href="http://scil.eventbrite.com/">Software Craftsmanship</a> group. This, for me, is a huge dream-come-true.</p>

<p>For years I've been looking for a good community around here to join, went to several meetups and looked around to no avail. My frustration grew about a year ago when I noticed the Chicago community is so buzzing with activity, people there have a meetup every day almost. That's why when <a href="http://twitter.com/urilavi">Uri</a> started organizing the first meeting I jumped in whole-heartedly.</p>

<p>In just a few months the meeting has influenced me quite a lot. First of all I got to meet a lot of new, smart and interesting people I never would have otherwise. It's not easy to find people that are as passionate about our profession as I am, yet our group didn't disappoint me.</p>

<p>The meetings also supply my need to pair with new people. Pair programming is a magical way of working and sharing knowledge, and I've yet to have a session with a new pair without picking up something new. I love the first minutes where we have to find a common language to get things started, and even more the high fives of getting a green bar.</p>

<p>Also, a good community is the best way to get feedback. I can say I'm trying to leech this to the max. I've already gave talks/sessions at 2 meetings, bugging people frequently on twitter and the mailing list. A varied community of like minded people allows you to get different outlooks and insights to things you've been neck-deep in for a while.</p>

<p>And last but not least, a good community might make magic stuff happen. I don't know how, but I'm sure our group had something to do with the fact some of us got to have dinner with <a href="http://twitter.com/unclebobmartin">Uncle Bob</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/schuchert">Brett Schuchert</a>, two awesome coders and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=as_li_tf_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=thcodu02-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=9325&amp;creativeASIN=0132350882">Clean Code</a><img src="http://www.assoc-amazon.com/e/ir?t=thcodu02-20&l=as2&o=1&a=0132350882" style="width: 0; height: 0; display: none; border: none !important;"> authors, on their last visit here.</p>

<p>Bottom line, be part of a community, and if there isn't one around you help start it! It's a great source of <a href="http://apprenticeship-patterns.labs.oreilly.com/ch04.html#kindred_spirits">kindred spirits</a>, an invaluable and rare resource!</p>

<p>You should <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheCodeDump">subscribe</a> to my feed and <a href="http://twitter.com/avivby">follow</a> me on twitter!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes from the 5th Israeli Software Craftsmanship Meeting]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.codelord.net/2010/12/17/notes-from-the-5th-israeli-software-craftsmanship-meeting/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-17T11:28:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.codelord.net/2010/12/17/notes-from-the-5th-israeli-software-craftsmanship-meeting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week I had the pleasure to attend to the 5th meeting of our Software Craftsmanship group, and boy what a meeting it was. For the first time we've tried a different format that is 100% hands-on and reduced someone-talking-with-slides time to a minimum.</p>

<p>The meeting was composed of 3 tables: a code review table where people actually brought code from home/work and discussed about with others, a TDD table where a veteran TDDer talked people through a Kata and a third table, led by yours truly, that aimed to introduce people to the concept of DRY and tackling some duplications problems.</p>

<p>Unfortunately for me, this means I couldn't take part in the other tables, but from what I could pick up I must say it was really fun getting so much positive feedback for a meeting.</p>

<p>The DRY table consisted of a Kata I've composed specifically to raise issues of duplication already a few minutes into it, which you can find <a href="/2010/12/11/serializer-kata-practicing-dry/">here</a>. It was amazing seeing people keep working on the Kata after the 1-hour dedicated to it was up, and I never expected to see such variety (Java, C#, Python, Ruby, JavaScript and PHP were all spotted)!</p>

<p>The slides from my (extremely) short introduction to DRY are available here:</p>

<script src="http://speakerdeck.com/embed/4f6dac1faa99e4002202a486.js"></script>


<p>You should subscribe to <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheCodeDump">my</a> feed and follow me on <a href="http://twitter.com/avivby">twitter</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Serializer Kata: Practicing DRY]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.codelord.net/2010/12/11/serializer-kata-practicing-dry/"/>
    <updated>2010-12-11T19:46:14+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.codelord.net/2010/12/11/serializer-kata-practicing-dry</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This kata is intended to help one practice the DRY principle (Don't Repeat Yourself). You can read more about DRY <a href="/category/dry/">here</a>.</p>

<p>A few notes:</p>

<ul>
<li>After completing a step in the Kata and before moving on to the next, take the time to make sure your code's duplication ≤ 0</li>
<li>For the sake of focus, you may ignore matters of character escaping, encoding, error handling, object graph cycles and the likes</li>
<li>Our focus is on <strong>reducing duplication</strong>, it is <strong>not finishing</strong> the kata</li>
</ul>


<p>In this Kata, our goal is to implement 2 simple object serializers. One serializer is to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML">XML</a>, the other is to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON">JSON</a>.</p>

<ol>
<li>Support serializing  a class without any members

<ol>
<li>To XML: EmptyClass -> &lt;EmptyClass&gt;&lt;/EmptyClass&gt;</li>
<li>To JSON: EmptyClass -> {}</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Add support for serializing a class' integer members

<ol>
<li>To XML: IntClass(a=1, b=2) -> &lt;IntClass&gt;&lt;a&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/IntClass&gt;</li>
<li>To JSON: IntClass(a=1, b=2) -> { "a": 1, "b": 2 }</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Add support for serializing a class' string members

<ol>
<li>To XML: StrClass(a="first", b="second") -> &lt;StrClass&gt;&lt;a&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;second&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/StrClass&gt;</li>
<li>To JSON: StrClass(a="first", b="second") -> { "a": "first", "b": "second" }</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Add support for serializing a class' other class members

<ol>
<li>To XML: CompositeClass(inner=(a=1)) -> &lt;CompositeClass&gt;&lt;inner&gt;&lt;a&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/inner&gt;&lt;/CompositeClass&gt;</li>
<li>To JSON: CompositeClass(inner=(a=1)) -> { "inner": { "a": 1 } }</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>


<p>If you found this interesting subscribe to my <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/TheCodeDump">feed</a> and follow me on <a href="http://twitter.com/avivby">twitter</a>!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
